[SPEAKER_00]: Dear Bhante, I understand the interest in freedom from suffering, but to aim for destroying rebirth entirely seems awfully extreme.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the answer really to just make myself stop existing?
[SPEAKER_00]: That seems unrelated to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, it's not your choice to stop existing, even if you desire that.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I would have talked about, one of the ways of being is to crave against being.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you certainly can't just desire to stop existing and on that account alone stop existing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Essentially, your existence has conditions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Greed, aversion and delusion, craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the same conditions that lead you to exist are the conditions that lead you to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, existence doesn't mean, like, you're...
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of circumstantial presence in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that were the case, then an arahant wouldn't be able to be alive and have given up existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Existence is determined by craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, if you want to be free from suffering, you want to be free from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you want to be free from craving, you're freeing yourself from the conditions for existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, why would we call it existence, if you could still exist and be free from existence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because that's how fundamental it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not that you're... it's not that you kind of... when you do certain things, pollution arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your entire being conscious, the way it occurs now, is polluted.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, your entire existence, the way it is now, is polluted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, even when it's in the most pristine and kind of seemingly passive state, it has all the same wrong implications that make it possible for you to engage in the coarse pollutions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you don't... as the Buddha said, there is no point where craving for being began, where the pollution began, and then afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's no point where there wasn't pollution and then pollution arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: The entire time, it's been there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically just have either confirmations, coarse confirmations of it, or
[SPEAKER_01]: Not-so-coarse confirmations of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why... it's... that's why the Buddha talked about it as existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that you get a sense of how broad the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't think that by preventing specific things, you're fixing the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, it's really... it's not really existence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you get a new existence?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you certainly can't... like, that's why you have stages of training.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't go from existing to not existing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing you can do is refine the way that you exist, up until that way of existing is refined enough for you to understand the complete cessation of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, initially, you exist by breaking precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You exist by actions of greed, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a more subtle state of existence,
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a state where those actions are absent, where they're given up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you still exist because you're still... well, you still have a sense of I am, you still have a sense of ownership, you are doing this restraint, you're doing these observance of the precepts and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But factually, it is a less coarse state of existence than the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: And to the same extent, it is a state of less suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because existence and suffering are inseparable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's a practical example of how you could understand, like, oh, yeah, I could still be alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: I would still be, you know, able to talk, speak, all these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, my existence would have diminished
[SPEAKER_01]: To the extent that I would have gone from breaking precepts to not breaking precepts as an actual internal practice, not just external compliance, which you could get to just by, I don't know, being hospitalized.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would refine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Refining your existence would diminish your suffering directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would then see for yourself, oh, so if this existence that has now been refined,
[SPEAKER_01]: If this would cease completely, in other words, if there was no sense of appropriation, no sense of duty, no sense of obligation towards any action whatsoever, then I would be completely free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't... like all the other considerations of what will happen to me, how will that feel,
[SPEAKER_01]: What do I have now that I have to remove?
[SPEAKER_01]: What was before that made this came to be?
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are what the Buddha called ayonisaṃnasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, those are distracting considerations that will only keep you within being, within suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's absolutely no need to even concern yourself with what will happen afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even imagine it, because that's exactly why it's called existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your present state of trying to imagine what the cessation of existence would be like, is within your current existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's polluted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of trying to imagine what it's like, you simply remove the conditions for your existence now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will know, whatever comes after, will not be able to be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that scares somebody still, the thought of ending existence, ending birth... Well, it is going to feel like death, like it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's not because they just misunderstand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, if I kind of find out what it actually means, just conceptually, then it won't be scary anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be scary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it will be scary to the extent that your existence is still coarse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for somebody who still holds the coarse existence of sensual being,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, from very warm, extremely warm, burning, to just complete freezing cold.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's going to be the extent of the contrast.
[SPEAKER_01]: If, on the other hand, that... that's why, in fact, the Buddha said, when he would teach the dhamma to people who would be very far on that extreme, for them, it would feel like death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they would be pulling their hairs out in... in despair, recognizing the extent of this... of that which, for them, would be annihilation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if your being is... has been refined, then it would be going from lukewarm to freezing, or from already pretty cold to freezing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it won't feel like that kind of precipice that you're... that you're throwing yourself into.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have less to lose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... and that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you are going to lose it anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when you think about death, you get pretty much that same sense of precipice that you would get if you thought about fully giving up your being.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are going to have to go through that anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, the problem is, you will go through it once, but then you will reacquire things that you will lose again, as happens in this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you build your whole career, build your whole
[SPEAKER_01]: lifestyle around certain things, you lose them entirely, and you could have just thought, oh, rather than repeating this again, let me just not build this tower that will fall.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but you don't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just build it up again and then it falls again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the distinction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have no choice but to lose your being, but to undergo that suffering, that loss of all that you have appropriated.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a question of whether you do it as a practice that will then free you from that entirely, like that you will not take up things again, or whether you just keep
[SPEAKER_01]: Gaining and losing, gaining and losing, gaining and losing indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what actual rebirth is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the... like... it's not just the physical manifestation of a being or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the result of them, as they say, taking up, appropriating the sense bases, appropriating the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're physically born.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you're physically born and then this appropriation happens.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, see, for example, when you think about
[SPEAKER_01]: What makes you suffer?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you suffer only when... Let's... let's take material possessions, which is the most relatable example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, do you suffer only when you actually lose things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or does the fact that you have to protect them already imply suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: And, actually, you realize the reason why you would suffer when you... when you would lose them is because you're trying to protect them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were not trying to protect them, even if you lost them, you wouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that need to protect is what your being is, and that's what your suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're not doing anything to protect them, so to speak?
[SPEAKER_01]: The internal need to do so is what the being is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you realize, oh, so being is what is suffering, not just the things that happen within being.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you... if... even if you never lost anything for a million years, the fact that you still need to protect, which is what your existence is, that is the fundamental suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, if you were to lose everything every single day, or, like, gain and lose things every single day, you wouldn't be suffering, because there would be no being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, should I just regularly switch out all my things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's... that's exactly the point of... that's what people would think.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if I just move from place to place, from monastery to monastery, as monks, change my habits, don't... don't hold on to the same things, I am not clinging to being.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not developing appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: The fundamental appropriation is towards your own body, towards your own senses, towards your own feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the one that everything else flows out from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, ask yourself, is there any tendency for me to try to protect what I feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: As if I have an entitlement in that regard.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the being that you have to abandon.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if switching things out is being done for that purpose, then you're actually making your being worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Also, you probably wouldn't be switching out the habit of switching things out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's giving you some kind of gratification, which you're protecting.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's your being.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that might be one of the only things that you're dependent on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Especially if you're a monk and that's your lifestyle.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would eventually become the one thing... like it's when... like when that monk... when the Buddha asked that wanderer who says... who said nothing pleases him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, well, that is the thing that pleases you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might have given up everything else, but your... the need to protect that feeling of gratification that you get is now condensed in this one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't want to be switching things around.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to be training yourself out of the entire principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what actual, for example, samādhi and jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many people think of it as a kind of replacement of your need for enjoyment, your need for gratification, a better way of satisfying that hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the cessation of that hunger, which the suttas explicitly state.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the abandonment of that entire principle of needing gratification, that would then lead you to peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, again, even if you think about it practically, when are you peaceful?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you... when you have been promised that nobody will steal your car.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or when you don't have a car to protect in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or when you have a car, but you don't need to protect it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the purification of being.